great wonderful hello Helena thank you
so much for making time to for us to
speak we've known each other for quite
some time now but it's it's great
opportunity to have this conversation on
the occasion of your wonderful book
coming out so let's let's dive straight
in with with a kind of question to the
current affairs because the
twenty-fifths conference of the parties
on climate change has just ended and I
think we're all desperately disappointed
that not very much has happened and in a
way it's surprising because we shouldn't
be disappointed with it anymore because
after 25 years of nothing happening one
would expect exactly that but I would
love you your view on tomate extent
you've been following what's been going
on and and how you see where we got to
at the end of this 25th conference
well I'm I've been saying for quite a
while that if we don't help people to
focus on the necessity for economic
change
I think we're doomed I am talking to
leaders in the business world and in
government who believe that they are
growing the economy for the voter when
they're actually growing it for a global
casino economy and most people are
actually becoming poorer in the sense
that they're actually having to work
harder and longer just to stay in place
and as people feel squeezed economically
and increasingly insecure about their
identity about the future about their
pension about their children's future
unfortunately many people are voting for
the leaders that stand up and say we're
going to grow the economy
forget about climate forget about this
forget about the poor we're going to
grow their time that we're going to grow
the economy make your nation
make you rich so I'm seeing a
frightening swing to the right
worldwide I'm seeing leaders who as I
say actually believe that they're being
pressured by the voter to grow the
economy as I see it
both governments and the average citizen
are being pressured by deregulated
capital a deregulated casino economy
that is pushing more and more and with
bigger and bigger sums of money in the
direction of highly energy intensive
resource intensive growth so to me you
know it's about waking up to the need
for a new economy movement and waking up
to the fact that it is happening there
is a new economy movement emerging which
I feel extremely hopeful about and very
happy to be a part of and then of course
I'm encouraging people to engage at the
local level to strengthen local
economies particularly around basic
needs and that's also a phenomenon
that's growing very rapidly so I don't
feel as depressed and unhappy about
Madrid as as other people do I mean
you've been one of the early voices to
say let's not get distracted
with all the other issues if we have a
structurally dysfunctional economic
system that is set up in a way that it
will transfer money from most of
humanity to an ever-smaller ever richer
group of very few and is structurally
designed in such a way that it needs
losers in order to generate these very
few winners we we are making a mistake
and we're getting distracted if we look
at all the symptomatic outcomes like
climate change ecosystems collapse and
so social inequality rise of right-wing
extremism all of that are ultimately
symptoms of an underlying disease which
is
a dysfunctional economic system and yeah
certainly for me 20 years ago you were
one of the first voices with whom I
could have not just read the books but
have a wonderful conversation when I was
a Jew maha um but what what I sense is
that that conversation is much more
mainstream now than it was 20 years ago
and even in a much more mainstream than
it was only five years ago like when I
when I read like you're also involved
with Gaia education in the global eco
village Network and when the education
first put out the online curriculum and
you you helped to write some of it and
that was really radical people like to
say we have a dysfunctional economic
system and really it's all this growth
imperative that is underlying all the
problems we're facing
um people were saying that's that's a
bit of an extremist curriculum but but
now I hear people even in the IMF under
saying that the economic system is
disrupt even the the founder of the
World Economic Forum says we need to
fundamentally redesign capitalism and so
how do you see that Square out there on
the one hand yes you get some countries
like the current American leadership
still driving for unbridled economic
growth but I feel more and more
countries are starting to talk a
different language well I feel there are
definitely more leaders and just
recently also from Iceland Scotland and
New Zealand them so there is definitely
absolutely at every level from the
environmental movement social movements
to government level and at the business
level a recognition something has to
change I think there is still at the top
the higher of people the power ladder
and the bigger and fatter salaries that
people have the more power they have
they are not only hampered by what many
people will think of almost as some kind
of you know psychopathic tendencies and
that that's how they got into place I
don't see that at all but what I say is
that as you go up the power ladder you
become more and more dependent on
secondhand third-hand quantified
information you see in the world through
a grid of numbers and within the culture
of power
the assumption is we're going to
continue more or less in the same
direction and and there is very little
information that is reaching them that
really spells out the need actually
could decentralization or localization
so that is anathema at that high level
and what I do see is a lot of language
about biodiversity but ecosystems about
rethinking and I've seen enormous shift
in the language within those corridors
of power in the last 30 years but in
actual fact I see a continuation and a
commitment to continuing fundamentally
in the same direction so for me what's
what's very interesting is yes you know
I got invited to speak at the Brussels
Economic Forum this year but is speaking
on the same panel with the head and
finance and economics in the EU and on
the same kind of lis you know someone
from Unilever and you know discussions
with the head of the IMF and so on
lastly I was invited to debate the chief
economist of the WTO and I have Joseph
Stiglitz come for tea actually this year
also so I had a lot of discussions with
the very you know people who are
definitely willing to rethink a bit but
I see a certain fundamentalism in their
thinking about what creates growth and
part of that is the conviction that
technology creates jobs the conviction
that growth is essential up to a certain
point so far too little concerned about
what's happened in India and China where
yes people have been lifted out of
poverty according to those
Germans so we look at the reality of how
they're living in slum like conditions
often very very unhealthy
I mean unhealthy just because of the air
pollution but also the quality of the
water the quality of life has plummeted
compared to most of the villages that
people lived in there were no paradise
but moving into the big cities and being
paid some kind of salary small or even
semi large you're still seeing a huge
reduction in the quality of life and
nothing that you could really talk about
as genuine improvement and that's
something that very few people are
actually looking at until now well this
is this is the other thing that that the
conversation around GDP being a
desperately inadequate measure of
performance of an economy or augs
certainly of success or progress we can
go into a whole nother conversation
around this whole progress mindset
anyway but but you mentioned two things
you mentioned that the higher level
political leaders basically get these
summaries that are all focused on
quantitative data that M and M also you
mentioned that the while the figures
might indicate that people come out of
poverty the quality of their lives so
the qualitative aspect doesn't actually
change positively and and so for me this
is so central to this shift that we need
to make now and that we're so stuck on
this adage what gets measured gets
managed and as things get tighter and
more problematic people want to see
quicker impact at scale and so all these
knee-jerk responses like how do we scale
it up and how do we measure it and what
are the impact indicators it to me
that's driving us all back into a
mindset that only looks at the
quantifiable when real quality of life
how we live our lives how we relate to
each other in our communities how do we
relate and heal our local ecosystems
they are all about
Changez and if we if we try to capture
those qualitative changes in quantities
we lose a lot but again oh no I think I
think Daniel one thing to keep in mind
to be honest is that there would be
quantifiable aspects that one could look
at for instance the degree of pollution
in the air the degree of pollution in
the water the actual you know quality of
the as I say the air pollution the water
pollution how much green they have
around them you know so that there would
be quantifiable elements that I think we
should also be sure to mention and to
insist on it's a very selective focus in
terms of quantification and don't forget
the whole thing is run on a system that
commercializes every aspect of life so
their various interconnected webs of
life being intervened in at every stage
to create you know a profit or
extractive capitalism and so it's sort
of an insanity in a way that any of us
are actually allowing GDP as a measure
to continue once you understood that it
really does increase with pollution with
ill health by the way that would be
another indicator that not be used this
is actually health including looking
honestly at obesity and it's linked to
sugar you know again that the actual
diet what are people getting in their
diet
what types of food cost less money
what types of food cost more money could
get lots of numbers there too and we'll
see this dreadful reality that around
the world processed old food from far
away will cost much less than fresh
healthy organic food why because of an
economic system that's selectively you
know looks at numbers in in an extremely
line and
stalked away how come like if we both
have experienced the shift at least in
the conversation over the last 10 15 20
years both were with regard to the need
to redesign in the economic system and
with the critique on GDP it's it's also
very popular now to admit that it's an
inadequate measure but then so many
wonderful people have done so much
wonderful work over the last 15 20 years
trying to build alternative indicator
and there's a whole host of them and and
and why aren't we shifting like well I
guess I think as you probably know I've
been dealing with this extremely
sensitive and difficult issue and that
is the way that so-called free trade
treaties have actually been about
deregulating the local economic activity
so deregulating global finance global
corporate activity the local media
pharmaceutical industry seed companies
fossil fuel industry the global
operators which are generally trans
national and multinational mobile
corporations have been asking for more
and more freedom from regulation and so
these treaties that to the general
public look like something with
beneficial or neutral or have actually
been an extremely destructive process
whereby governments have progressively
given these giants the exons the
Monsanto's the large bands
more and more freedom and I think
particularly after 2008 when everyone in
the world knew what is going on in this
finance world with these trading
mortgages some lives of people you've
never seen and completely irresponsible
behavior the whole world knew that we
needed to regulate the banks but
tragically instead what's happening
further deregulation however this whole
issue of the way that these giants have
been given
more freedom and totally removed from
regulation while at the same time
pressuring governments to increase the
spending on global infrastructure that
favors them and makes them richer
and and they have also together with
governments been part of encouraging
more and more regulation at the local
regional and national level so even
national industries are place-based
they're scrutinized to some extent and
they have met with regulations and
particularly the small players
particularly small farmers small primary
producers have been burdened with more
and more heavy regulation and these same
place face businesses at the national
level having squeezed for taxes in the
meanwhile those taxes are used to
subsidize an infrastructure and
generally business as usual for giant
global corporation so we have a
completely unfair playing field which
around the world and I don't know any
country virtually here that hasn't gone
along with it we have this situation
where those that produce the most energy
you pollute the most of most resource
intensive and it actually overall employ
cleaver people and these entities have
grown in power and worldwide as I said
earlier we see in reality a situation
that even during periods of growth from
national GDP increasing the majority
people are getting poorer
so I believe that once this sort of
genie really gets out of the bottle
there could be a huge AHA experience for
the movements the social environmental
movements but also for political and
economic leaders but we need to do
everything we can to spare this out in a
clear way in a compassionate way it
really is primarily about blind
we're allowing many many leaders to
comfortably remain blind but you know we
I would say at the level of you know
social and environmental rules really
haven't done the job because we've not
been looking globally enough there's
been very little awareness of how
enormous and fundamentally important
this trajectory has been in over the
last thirty years not only taking us
into a world of four greater increases
in pollution and co2 emission but also a
situation where most people now have
lost all faith and democracy you know
this basically seeing their governments
promised to they're blue in the face as
they seek election to look after their
citizens and once in power they're
looking after global billionaires so we
have a big job to do to get this
holistic message out and without Tim and
I saying without assuming that either
any individual corporation is to play
any more any in particularly individuals
I really do feel that this should be
done with a great deal of compassion and
understanding that as long as the world
is blind
well this casino economy will continue
and we don't we really need to urgently
get on with this task to expose the
realities of it so how would you like
because we I think we're both very much
aligned with this need for working
locally in the sense of that that really
it is all about real ocol izing and re
regionalizing but in order to achieve
that we need increased global
collaboration among all the actors to
clear the playing field too because as
you as you alluded to it right now
anybody like my example here on the
island of Majorca M if even if we all
agreed and try to build a example of a
regional economy at island scale to in
trees local food production local food
sovereignty to manage our water here on
the island in a way that is sensible and
and that people have ownership over to
produce decentralized renewable energy
and create a transport system that is
based on public transport and non non
polluting all of those shifts would
actually run against global regulations
and would compete in an unfair market
with cheap imports from afar so so where
do you see the key entry points like if
you you said talked to Joseph Stiglitz
and people at the IMF and the WTO what
would be your message to them of saying
these are the four or five key leverage
points in terms of externalities and
subsidies where we could really shift
the system and enable people to have a
more regional eyes real oak alized
likelihood again you know talking into
those in power I would be looking at the
urgent need to renegotiate trade
treaties to start a process of
re-regulation at the global level and
this will happen once governments really
are held to account by their citizens
you know because as individuals in
government you know you often have this
revolving door where they were you know
as an empty later on become CEO
corporation so in a personal level a
certain lesson interest in just
continuing business as usual but at the
national level and you know the level of
civic society we really must insist on a
process of really regulate inand it's
not something that's going to suddenly
overnight close down every multinational
company but the end goal would be that
society shapes business rather than
business as it is currently doing now
shaping society and shaping a sort of a
democracy which is not democracy at all
when you have global media having such
influence in national debates even even
forgetting about their lobbying and the
funds that are directly you
to manipulate the government process the
lack of control of media and so on is
also fundamental part of it and that
again we as Civic Society members we
don't want to leave that control
entirely to centralized governments we
want to see civic society at the table
and part of the process of shaping the
new agenda so the hope would but I mean
with four people in power you know the
need to start really regulating the
banks and corporations it's something
like yeah we can give them a lot of
evidence as to why that is necessary and
equally important is to look at
systematically deregulating at the local
and national level of course selectively
not across the board we want absolutely
one certain genuine environmental
protection we want genuine concern for
public health and safety but what we
have found in working across the world
in the local trying to build up local
food economies is that the best people
to monitor you know what kind of seeds
what kind of hygiene standards are
necessary on their farms in the
processing industry in the restaurant
would best be monitored and control
Wiley local groups because even things
like the centralized national organic
standard ends up incapable of actually
taking responsibility for what's
happening at the distance so we need you
know to understand the need for more
experience or knowledge and more
localized ways of monitoring and they
and they the ideally will be part of a
tiered system where this also extends up
to the global level and in both
direction you know from the local to the
bill will go to local accountability and
disability when you say the need to
reregulate and the the key that I mean
wait we're currently still in
world where despite more governments
committing verbally to taking action on
climate change off the top of my head
something like seventy year or more
percent of global energy subsidies are
still subsidizing fossil fuel industry
and then there's another 10/15 that
subsidized nuclear and renewables
they'll get a very small part of the
energy subsidy pie and similarly we
still have conditions where a kerosene
for four flights isn't taxed properly
where the most polluting of all fossil
fuels the bunker oil of large ships is
is not regulated in a proper way so what
what specific entry points for re
regulations would you give priority if
you if you said like these are the five
that we really need to get going on well
I think if we you know in order to do
any of them I don't think any of them
would be easier to implement them the
really regulation of global trade but
certainly one of the things that I said
we looked at is the fact that right now
every business and this again these are
operating at the national level because
the other ones are regulated but at the
national level they are all being
encouraged to use energy and technology
instead of employing people because it's
been fundamental to the modern economy
to do so and because there was a belief
the technology will always alleviate
hard work and there was this vision of
us not having to do any work so it's
gone unabated from the beginnings of the
modern economy shifting that to
encourage businesses instead to employ
people wherever possible and where we
desirable because there are instances
yes where technology can be a benefit
but once we start looking holistically
and we understand the reality of small
ascared diversified farms for instance
being one of the most attractive places
for people to work so there are several
examples of being
who choose to leave the Silicon Valley
jobs or whatever whatever they might
have been to farm farming and a
diversified scale and with the
appropriate number of people two areas
of land or animals these one of the more
enjoyable things that we can do it's
something that's in our DNA we were
connected to that and it's as part of
our lives for a whole evolution so I'm
seeing one of the most inspiring
movements of all is this sort of new
farmers movement but anyways shifting
shifting away from encouraging every
business to use ever more energy and
technology instead of employing people
would be one of the most important
things we could do right now we don't
because we're not looking at the
economic trajectory
we're not understanding why most
teachers are now so burdened with
bureaucracy they barely have time to
spend on it some students most doctors
are sitting looking at their computer
screen instead of their patients and
where the teachers are doctors they all
have less time to do what they're meant
to be doing why it's because of
centralized system using the computer
industry and the tool that seemed to be
for many people seemed to be a great
advantage it has allowed for this
centralized control and power and the
management of more and more people at
distance and it has led to this terrible
time pressure competition and not only
energy intensive technologies but we're
talking now about technologies that use
more and more rare earth minerals and
very very scary trajectory I guess
you've heard about mining the
Mediterranean where the minerals needed
for electric cars we have not had an
honest full cost accounting of these
technological systems that have been
presented to us particularly in the last
3040 years as huge advantage advances
for him in fine and now we need to start
looking really honestly at the
minerals that the resources the energy
and what is doing to society so but
there would be one intervention one of
the most important laws would be to
immediately moving away from what we
call insane trade because we have these
inverse mechanisms that favor energy use
instead of human labour we have this
situation where supermarkets routinely
flight fish to the other side of the
world to be indeed born flight back
apples to be washed flown back again I
had my eyes open to this first in Sweden
in the 70s and I it was because I become
aware of this through work in Ladakh and
Bhutan you know in these ancient
cultures that still had their own local
economy and then I saw the advent of the
outside economy and how it raises
unemployment and pollution overnight and
I saw how suddenly butter traveling from
the other side of the Himalayas more
than a week's travel in the drives in
the local marketplace themselves for
half the price of butter from a 5 min 5
minute walk away from the farm so that
opened my eyes to it I go back to Sweden
and I find that at that time in the 70s
they were sending potatoes by road to
Italy to be washed put in plastic bags
and sent back again by Road now this is
happening by air and is happening across
the world and equally idiotic and
criminally wasteful is that because of
the whole nature of this deregulated
global system favoring the
multinationals countries are choosing
instead of using their own food to feed
their people their own building
materials their own fibers for all the
basic needs
they were importing exporting the same
product you see if everybody sat down
tomorrow and ate their breakfast from
food that had been grown and processed
and sold in their own country
no multinational would make money but
because
craziness of favoring the only trade
countries now with Chile import and
export beef wheat no water right now the
UK exposed 20 tonnes of bottled water to
Australia Australia exposed 20 tons of
bottled water to the UK and what is
almost enough to drive me mad is that
we've tried to raise awareness about
this for a long time and sadly not even
most climate groups bring this up
instead they go along with an agenda
that blames the individual and that
creates so much self blame and despair I
think if people could have their eyes
open to what's going on they would feel
a great sense of relief and hopefully
join you know what I call big-picture
activism so how do you because on the
one hand we have these massive changes
that are necessary at the regulatory
level of how we deal with things
globally but then there's this massive
potential of reenergized in revitalizing
local community and networks of local
communities within their bioregional at
the regional scale and um you know very
often quoted Buckminster Fuller quote
don't fight the existing system build an
alternative one that makes the old one
obsolete that it probably is a little
bit of both and we need to lobby it at
the global level to change these
regulations but where do you see hope
like particularly with regard to your
new book local is our future and where
do where do you see the opportunity in
the meantime as we're trying to lobby
changes at international level and a
national level for people to really take
back the power at the local level and
strengthen local economies and
strengthen local food sovereignty and
although all those aspects you name a
number in your book but I'd love to hear
that correctly yeah you know as you know
I was one of the
co-founders of both the global eco
village Network and the education
process in the eco village Network and
so for me for you know 45 years it was
very clear that so many benefits would
come from stronger local economies
including the villages were possible but
I guess for me it was clear that for so
many people that would be rather
difficult tasks and so I felt that the
broader process of localization is what
many people couldnt and should engage in
so I'm we're trying to encourage people
to start the process of reconnecting
consumerist producers and the middlemen
it's not a question of getting rid of
the middleman we have many examples
where local farmers selling to a local
shop that in turn sells to local
community
consumers can work extremely well and we
have a lot of examples of also more
direct relationships to farmers markets
there are now more and more projects
which we feel you know for us having
helped to catalyze these initiatives in
so many countries we are just amazed and
thrilled to see that they are
flourishing and they are continuing to
grow so we see this as a vitally
important focus for most people who
today are feeling overwhelmed if you're
depressed about Madrid but just happen
in Madrid I would urge them to also look
at our website as well as my book to see
examples of this sort of initiatives
that they can maybe join or start once
you get a different set of lenses on and
you realise the importance of this
shortening of distances as a
counterweight to what's been going on
with these heavy subsidies and so on
once you stop putting those lenses on
you'll see there is so much more
happening than you would have thought
and I hope you'll join me in feeling
deeply
encouraged by a fundamentally different
narrative from the dominant one the
dominant narrative is that this is mess
that we have the xenophobia the
anti-immigrant feeling the climate
change with mountains of plastic
pesticide so it disappears up in space
you know it just feels like an endless
string of dreadful frightening crises
once we start realizing that they
emanate from the same economic
fundamentals and we see that the
shortening of distances is a systemic
antidote you know particularly if you
join the local food movement you will be
helping to restore not only why not
you'll be helping to renew the water
sources will be helping to reduce the
need for energy you'll be helping
structurally to stimulate market
pressure that in turn stimulates the
uses towards diversity and diversity is
a fundamental principle of life so this
is why these local food initiatives are
so much more important than many people
realize but I do absolutely feel that
there's so much that we can do that it's
very real that's very significant and
it's about changing the I - of we we're
becoming part of a systemic collective
shift the community initiative instead
of just saying okay I'm going to shop
local we wanted you to actually be part
of this sort of movement and really help
to strengthen and join and role that
local food movement but along with that
now there are more and more initiatives
that build on that foundation and local
business alliances are being formed
local finance schemes local energy as
well community energy initiatives most
of it on a human scale that provides the
structures that allow us to be far more
intelligent far more wise in our choices
we see
the structures in a way that prevents
the very dangerous manipulation that's
going on in the global economy where
we've been led to believe that you know
buying that new eco product or well
there are many things we've been led to
believe you know that if we drive our
car less and if we don't go on holiday
in an airplane that's how we're gonna
solve the climate crisis but these
things all misleading and they were not
looking at the real issues always what
was happening to the economy in terms of
what industry was doing and what type of
business and industry our governments
were promoting I do want to say though
Daniel I want to make it clearer and I'm
so I find it very difficult to really
stress this and not somehow I'm not
talking about us also lobbying
government I'm talking about encouraging
people to start joining and creating
localization initiatives with a very big
focus on food and farming and with that
agroforestry so also trees which are
important part of it and including
animals as part of diversified system
that if you study that more you will see
that this is a way of regenerating and
healing the earth
but in terms of changing the bigger
trajectory and what governments do I'm
talking more about something along the
lines of extinction rebellion that we
need to have civic society at the table
we are not just going to be lobbying
existing politicians and though we are
going to build up a movement that
demands civic society involvement and
that will probably mean in many cases a
change in government it will mean in you
know we need to be put in place and new
politics and new framing that is linked
to the new economy understanding and in
some places that's starting to happen
and you know particularly up there at
the local level they are very
interesting political
Princeton's Froome I'm sure you heard of
the independence for Truman in young a
very exciting initiative where where all
the representatives went away from Party
politics to represent their local
community and with that were able to do
very creative very positive things with
a very limited budget so we need to
essentially really capture democracy
it's not just about lobbying government
and the first step is to create more
awareness in the movement the social and
environmental movement and one of the
first steps there is to move away from
single issues for a single issue focus
we have to have a flag that clearly
excessive people this is not just about
climate as an issue out there this is
about your livelihood it's about your
child's potential for some kind of
secure livelihood it's about some kind
of you know cultural and way of life
that provides security and that moves
you away from this intensely competitive
unstable system to create more secure
and balanced relationships but how you
mentioned extinction rebellion and I
mean that's one of the the big hopeful
shifts of the last even really the last
year or 14 months and with the
extinction rebellion and Friday's for
future somehow activating a lot more
people into this discourse and at the
same time and it is very focused on the
climate change issue and it is very
focused on I kind of enough we don't
want any more of this we have a right to
a future em to my mind
it I don't I haven't seen enough yet the
shift of these the people who have now
been activated into the hopeful local
regional movements of saying let's begin
to build the new system that makes the
old obsolete let's claim our right
to civic participation in government
governance and in politics at the local
level and and then link up globally to
also claim it at the global level but
it's yeah it's this shitty from being
against something to a concerted
strategy of putting something new into
place that yeah you talk but I would say
that actually you know where I slightly
differ with you I I worry a little bit
about the idea that many people now have
as they get interested in localization
and so then they think y'all its first
build up the local and then let's look
at linking up and changing the bidding
system I am trying to urge people to do
both not every person necessarily but
you know we're trying to urge people to
get together in local groups and they
are jointly look at what can we do as a
community initiative and also how can we
contribute to getting the word out about
the reality of lots of local examples
that show that we must go local for the
future the parity has to do with
biodiversity there's an imperative there
that we just can't escape it's about
what actually can be life enhancing and
how that relates to local knowledge
systems it relates to experiential
knowledge you know there's some multiple
reasons where we're going to have to go
local we may end up doing that just
through crises but thank goodness there
are a lot of initiatives that are
happening access it ii but i but i am
trying to encourage people to
simultaneously at least as a group or at
least be linked to groups that are
trying to get the word out about the
localizing path as a strategy for a
political shift and so it's a little bit
like you know many spiritual movements
thought first we have to have placed on
the inside and then we can create a
peace movement what i've always been
saying is the inner and the outer are
completely connected will then be much
better off lupus parted
both ends hmm and for instance in terms
of inner transformation I love to use
this prism project near us in Devon
where you know prisoners who have their
whole lives have been hardened and only
known competitive culture helped to
basically build a sense of connection
and community to sit down and have a
conversation over a meal in a way that
they've never done you know a prisoner
will say I've never in my life
experienced people actually talking to
me being interested in what I was
feeling or thinking and these same
prisoners have gained that sense of
community also to growing food and
learning that skill and learning the joy
of being really productive and seeing
the result in a deep ultimately
spiritual connection to the living world
so things like that can transform people
on the inside but it starts with as it
were an external localization project so
I feel you know I I also feel that with
with extinction rebellion that they are
beginning now to change and I agree with
you it should be in two directions one
of them is to understand and embrace the
localization movement the other one is
to put out a message to people that is
beyond just climate that is saying we
are not just about climate alia we are
about an economic transformation that is
about your livelihood this is not
something that's separate from you so I
think that message of the new economy
moment and the potential through
localization the potential particularly
with policy change how really quite
rapidly we could see huge benefits if we
were able to get more support from the
dominant system so we are seeing some
local governments and some regional
governments now you know
beginning to change and it's very
interesting because it's so clearly was
there pressured there closer to the
ground they're often more aware of the
environmental impact they're more aware
the social impact of what they do and so
they are responding earlier than
national governments I I'm quite
convinced that if we have time that we
will ultimately move in the right
direction what worries me is that this
is juggernaut them you know basically
fake capital capital created through
debt and just out of thin air not a link
to any resources not been to any real
wealth but just because we've allowed
the banks to become so powerful the
global that they're able to create
masses of money which is used almost
like bonds you know landing in local and
national economies pushing everything in
the direction of exploitation pollution
etc so that creates an urgency that
needs I think we need to try to get
there what I call the big picture out as
soon as possible well let me just
briefly get back to like I wasn't in any
way suggesting we need to first do this
and then do the other and and also like
everything he just said I've also been
working on for 20 years and that that we
need to work on on both ends at the same
time and but then for me the the issue
with like you mentioned diversity is one
of the key measures of a healthy system
one thing that I was slightly
disappointed with regard to extinction
rebellion is you know they have these
ten principles and one of the principles
is regenerative culture and we need a
regenerative culture and then that the
sub line says creating cultures that are
healthy resilient and adaptable in that
sub line M proves to me that they've
actually taken this from for my book
because it's exactly those three
adjectives in that I use in that
sequence but what they didn't do and
this is like I'm excited and I
not about kindness and some author
having some sort of quibbles that they
didn't quote me and but I'm a little I'm
excited that they picked it up but what
I'm worried about is that they turned
the plural of regenerative cultures into
a single because this is this is one of
these issues that slightly because it
came out of the UK and there's wonderful
people involved and I am so glad
extinction rebellion exists and I'm
fully supportive of them and there is an
yet again by using the singular where we
have it again not decolonial izing the
mind enough and were pretending that
it's a bunch of the English activists
who've created the new thing that now
everybody has to take on instead of
saying no regeneration and coming back
to this this wealth and the potential of
local community and local ecosystems to
provide for nature and us as part of
magic is all about the bio cultural
uniqueness of place it's all about these
regenerative cultures in all their
diversity giving expression to a healthy
system and in it if we ever managed just
let me little bit more of that random
yeah and it's also about this that when
we understand that it is about creating
many of these diverse regenerative
cultures in place then we can also see
that in all our diversity of faiths of
religious beliefs of niggas we we don't
have enough time to get to a point where
all of humanity agrees on what to do we
will begin to read treasure our
diversity of opinion also as part of
life's diversity of adaptability and yet
find that higher ground of working in
the same direction to heal the planet
and heal our relationship with each
other and the planet and I'd love to
just hear your perspective on that well
I love the fact that you say that plural
and I have to tell you there are very
few Westerners who understand that so I
felt in that you know but I've been at
it for 45 years and that's been it's a
big big problem particularly in the
angular
always lack of awareness but even
generally in Europe too little
understanding of the need for plural
therefore the diversity of cultures and
particularly that deep connection
between people and the place the natural
place that they know where they live and
with it that they emanate from so and
that's of course fundamental to
localization that's why localization is
so fundamental and why your knowledge
systems need to be decentralized and
then you get into a whole discussion
about the role of science today and and
again why their latest techno systems
have to be questioned because they tend
to suit global centralized power
structures and and that's another whole
discussion we don't want to get into now
but it is certainly something we need to
be discussing and people need to be
thinking about and I feel to me it's so
much about awareness of this bigger
picture you know it's it's a real
wake-up that can be helped when people
like us try to put up this bigger
picture when I see there's some you know
as people quite intuitively react to the
problems of the toxic monarch on to the
consumer monoculture in many ways they
are returning to place they're returning
it happens in many different ways but
you know even it's starting to listen to
their bodies they start listening more
to their bodies and me as you know they
often know much better than they over
intellectualized mind so there is a way
in which I think that humankind would
come back to diversity in place and
indeed wisdom and a deep and a joyous
connection to life itself well he's
doing that it's just that we need to
help try to speed up the process because
this truly artificial man-made
juggernaut which is a techno economic
system that's taken on a life of its own
that
literally is run by algorithms by robots
very very dangerous system is escalating
and that system may be the very last
thing to collapse so we should not wait
for that system to collapse and and as
many people do believe that it will
because we might very well have another
2008 2009 but that doesn't mean the
system collapses because it will be
fixed in the same way was fixed before
if we the people and we the movements
don't wake up but how do you deal with
because there's one you we mentioned
there's two more things that I would
like to address before we wrap up one of
them is the the danger that I've
observed in recent years that was become
possible now is that you've like I
certainly have found myself in the
conversation at a local level with
people that all seem to initially agree
yes we need to build food sovereignty we
need to meet most of our communities
essential needs closer to home we need
to value our local ecosystems in our
local culture more all stuff that I
would immediately sign on the dotted
line for and then suddenly other little
bits of the discourse come in and you
realize you're actually talking to
relatively right-wing real localization
groups that that are coming at a similar
agenda but from a very very different
angle that is kind of against another
and is actually quite xenophobic and
like you could find right-wing German
Nazis supporting a real localization
agenda you can find an extremist Catalan
independence movement people that are
doing wonderful work but by doing it as
an opposition to another em jump on that
on that bandwagon have you have you come
across this tension yourself and how do
we work with that well I have I mean but
I must say what I've come across much
more is people on the left is
zooming that localization looks like
that
I'm trying to think if I've known any
people who are really truly on a
localization agenda and I remember
particularly around who we are talking
about becoming self-reliant we're not
talking about having a nice farmers
market to add to everything else that
you've been important so I don't think
I've actually met you know right-wing
people who were actually truly on the
localization agendas I say they might
have liked the addition of a nice
farmers market in something so and and I
think the fear on the left is very much
a fear of attack that the assumption is
that if you care about the local that
you then you know probably ante the
outside where I think we have a lot to
talk about is the role of tourism and
even to some extent immigration in
threatening local communities and their
ability to look after themselves so I've
tried for years to explain that I've
seen Irish curious at Americans who were
coming in in large numbers and buying up
their villages that's in Swedes you know
angry at the Germans I've seen Welsh
people burning the houses of Londoners
that we're moving in to their into Wales
and buying a houses so I think we've got
to look there at the need for
communities everywhere to have more
control over their lives and at probably
quite a natural reaction when local
communities feel overwhelmed and
marginalized by outside forces now when
it comes to immigrants and so much of
that is exacerbated by again media and
other outside interests in saying that
your problem is due to them to the
immigrants and
and people then assume that their
hardship is due to that's it for me the
clarity about why most communities are
feeling disempowered and marginalized
the clarity about even with tourism you
know now in Venice I think they have
something like 50 million tourists a
year and there have been anti tourist
demonstration well this is a consequence
again in this economic system that is
extracting wealth out of every local
community so from my point of view
having a vision of localization which is
completely about the the message of this
human race should have the right to feed
itself you know local communities should
have the right to provide food for
themselves first and not be forced into
this trade relationship which started
with slavery slavery certainly
colonialism will be created with nearly
imbalances that this system has fed off
and through that created a lot of anger
and inequality god not of localization
as a problem but of globalization as the
problem you gave a really good key word
that word slavery because in many ways
economic globalization has been a second
round of colonialization and of putting
the system in place I mean I don't know
if you just I just recently saw this
movie the spider's web that that looked
at the the British if you haven't seen
it I highly recommend it it looks at how
basically after the fall of the British
Empire the City of London with its
peculiar strange historic that goes back
to 1066 or 1067 where the City of London
bought this new likelike special deal of
being separate from the rest of the UK -
with regard to certain levels of
regulations and but but really very much
since the fall of the British Empire em
after the first second world war there
was an active move by the
the power elites in the UK to create a
new system of control that was based on
the financial markets and and when you
when you mentioned migration my mind
also went to we need to in this global
awareness raising and we need to also
understand that most of these migrations
we now observe are really triggered by
colonialism and that the second wave of
colonialism lydian either they
environmentally driven migrations or
there's social even the economically
driven migrations are all really the
imbalance that we've created between the
global north and the global south and so
either we address our historical debt
and we cancel the debt of the global
self and we stop this conversation of
are you will support you when you have
when you because the the sad and tragic
aspect of all this is that having been
raped and pillaged twice by colonialism
and then neoliberal economic
globalization now climate change is
hitting those global South nations and
people align islands in the Pacific and
in the Caribbean much harder than the
wealthy extractive more than powers that
have benefited twice from this
extractive although actually I mean
interesting enough I think that is not
necessarily true now if you look at
what's happening in California and you
look at what's happening it doesn't mean
it's not hitting India and Africa and so
how do we address this global imbalance
of the the past wrongdoings in order to
to actually move forward together as one
humanity because what's very important
there is not to blame the current
generation of white people for what
their ancestors did nor even to glorify
the current generation of people from
the global south or indigenous people
that are no
longer you know living in an indigenous
way let's try to really shift away from
the politics of identity and let's look
at how we're trying to work for a system
that is truly more just and equitable
and how actually I think there's a very
important task to be done which is which
is to show that now the suffering in
both the industrialized countries and in
the less industrialized countries is
such that in many ways those people in
the global South or in so-called
undeveloped world that have not yet been
pulled into cities are in many ways
better off than many of us they have
more skills they have more ability to
provide for themselves and they're
actually
leaders in trying to build more
localized economies that serve their own
needs what's preventing it is huge
psychological pressures as well as
government pressures as well as
regulations that are trying to destroy
that self-reliance and trying to destroy
those regional economies but we should
be very aware man it's extremely
important for us to have a deep dialogue
between the most urbanized
industrialized parts of the world and as
it were released industrialized and
organized and to try to show that they
should not feel as they are made to feel
every day through schoolbooks through
television through films through AdWords
they are told that they are stupid and
backward and know nothing and are nobody
and so there's a huge psychological
pressure on them to want to emulate the
urban consumer culture and as I said
earlier in most cases as they move into
the cities which as you know many of
which are you know 20 million 40 million
Beijing is actually 16 million now with
18 satellite cities their absolute
nightmare so huge amount work needed to
communicate
more deeply and and I would say now move
beyond also the discourse of rich
country poor country which is
particularly misleading when it comes to
the climate debate because we were told
that poor countries shouldn't lower
emissions as well as rich countries and
that was was industry was moving from
Europe and North America into the poor
countries to use the poor labor and then
to transport things even more and create
even more poverty on there's pollution
to like environmental records and
animals because heavy production as a
myself but all of this still this is the
last point that and because I know that
you worked with Noam Chomsky in early
days of your career and and recently
because we also mentioned the media
earlier and the role of the media and
recently I came across and somebody
mentioned to me that the Marshall
McLuhan apparently at one point said
that the trend of globalisation of the
of media would inevitably lead in the
future to a renaissance of the local and
and I which which I am wondering to what
extent when we look at building
alliances at local and regional level um
and we want to create new participatory
Civic democracy movements there is this
issue that because our education systems
and particularly the media have
brainwashed a large part of humanity
into believing this growth imperative in
this progress story and have inoculated
us with this highly competitive
misunderstood Darwinism of competition
and so on they like when when you
actually get to a point of saying no we
all should have more of a say and hear
everybody's voice the voices you hear
are feeding back the results of
pretty bad media work and education work
of 3040 years so when you then do these
multi-stakeholder multi at the
collaborations you actually hearing a
lot of misinformation in the room and
it's it's kind of a like when you look
at the history of kind of referendums
and in participatory democracy very
often demagogues have got into power
because of that and so it's this for me
there's a big big tension of I not
ideologically but idealistically I would
love for all of us to sit in a circle
and make decisions that hear everybody's
voice and every time I've actually done
it with a very diverse group and not a
pre-selected group of my type of people
I very quickly got frustrated with the
amount of ignorance in the room that is
based on this mediatic and bad education
manipulation of thirty years of of
telling the wrong story so how how do
you see that tension working out as we
try to build a better well I mean one
thing I think that we need to be very
clear about is that again through very
sophisticated think tanks using billions
of dollars our the pressure on the
movements in the West it had been who
are you democratic do you have a
completely level consensus you know
structure in your New York movement in
your NGO and we don't realize that we're
being told to be the perfect democracy
inside a system that is pressuring us
every day to just survive to pay the
mortgage to pay rent so we're in a
system that is fundamentally
hierarchical and every day exerting more
pressure so we have to be very very
aware of what what is actually going on
here we're actually being manipulated
into a supposed you know perfect
democratic structure which is from my
experience has never existed ever you
know I feel there's a lot
learn from indigenous cultures as as I
did in in Ladakh of Bhutan and there
there was very very clean clear waste
that everyone did not have accepted the
same voice and particularly you know
that the elders knew better we will
leave you were they were very lucky you
know they were living in structures
where things had been tested and tried
for generations so for most things there
wasn't even a need for a discussion and
when there was you know there were
people who were clearly looked up to and
so let's be able to care careful here
and let's try to to realize that we
cannot create the change we need to see
by trying to be as I say well this
completely level consensus making
structure to me does not make sense
however having said that I think that
the of course we want to move in a much
more democratic direction as we're
trying to create these new models and
these new ways of living
but the interesting thing for me is that
in the localization movement
particularly again around film and
mostly with the business alliances or
we've actually succeeded in finding a
way of beginning to build structures
where people become interdependent
coming from very different places so
typically the local food initiatives
like farmers market I started using the
conventional currency very often the
farmers are quite conservative if not
right-wing and they've been trained to
believe that I've got to go in this
direction towards chemicals and moral
culture in many cases when they started
joining the farmers market it was
because they were struggling so badly
and someone had the idea let's try to do
a local market and I've had the great
joy of seeing how they suddenly find
themselves in this new structure where
the consumer doesn't mind if there's
some specs on the apples they absolutely
don't want every apple or avocado to be
exactly the same size so they say there
is this sudden newly formed relationship
and dialogue between more dreamy lefty
if you like and more conservative and in
the meanwhile they don't have to sit
around as part of a consensus is making
stakeholder situation that to a great
extent as I say has been imposed on us
by vested interests so and to wrap up I
just want to bring attention back to
your book and and well do you wanna just
briefly like one thing that I would love
to hear is at the very end the last
chapter of the book is is a conversation
you just had not so long ago with one of
the the great elders of the movement and
and particularly the the need to come
back to the land and to re-engage with
agriculture in a way that allows us to
really put humanity back into
nature as gardeners of landscape as
protectors of landscape so can you just
often memory maybe pull out a couple of
highlights of that conversation with
wendell berry and if there's anything
else you want to say about the book and
how to engage with your work
more deeply it would be useful to share
that with listeners well I've known
Wendell for a very long time he's on our
advisory board and he's been one of the
soul mates you know one thing I think in
our conversation even now where we
differ a little bit is that he hasn't
been involved globally you know the way
I have and so I used to slightly argue
with him because he would say no only
think locally and act locally you're not
saying but on the other side of the
world I'm seeing people who don't know
anything about what's happening here
being very misled about what we're up to
and and the other way around and this is
feeding into this normal system so so
that's partly death so that's where we
have a slightly different point of view
but he is of course one of the you know
one of the absolute sort of pioneers and
leaders of the localisation movement and
it's just so thrilling to know that he's
still healthily and happily actually
farming at his age and he's has got a
great sense of humor and he's an
excellent writer so I really recommend
if people haven't read his essays and
books a wonderful writer and so he's
been a huge gift to the movement and
it's thrilling to see a he's very
respected in thoughtful workers in
America but very very wonderful and in
terms of the book in general yeah it is
different in that way and it's in my my
sort of you know problem is that I'm
trying to to say something and to do
something that it's extremely unusual I
mean I would say unique I don't know
anyone any any other voice
another organization that has been
promoting localization from a global
perspective from global experience and
for a global movement and and this has
also led to what some people might think
of as hypocrisy that we end up in my
tiny organization organizing conferences
and several different countries and
several different continents and that we
actually believe that people who want to
try to understand what's happening in
the world and want to really do
something to contribute we would
actually urge them if possible to spend
some time in both the least developed
parts of the world and the most
developed because that's I think where
you get sort of clarity about the system
at work in terms of yeah I feel like I'm
working with - in visibilities -
invisible world I'm working with the
hand of the economy you know the
invisible hand of the economy which has
become a political economy and very very
few activist organizations have been
focusing on that global system and its
global impact it's very difficult to
problem-solve its global impact when
you're only in one place and so I've
seen that that invisible hand of the
economy the proponents of it often have
a lot of global experience and I'm
moving around globally be they diplomats
be they heads of business or whatever
but they're looking at it through that
lens of numbers and absolutely wedded to
their assumptions about grow on the
other hand I'm dealing with another in
disability which is the inner workings
of our deep spiritual emotional
psychological even physical connection
to the living world the the world within
us the world the natural world that we
are deeply connected to and I believe
that we long to come home to
we have been cut off and separated from
the natural world
you know images you know in a high-rise
building with windows you can't open
no sign of nature around you controlled
environment we have ended up sick lonely
and longing to come back home and that
journey back home is about rebuilding
this these invisible connections that
give us a deep sense of satisfaction and
meaning and I feel you know very lucky
to be inviting people to what I call the
economics of happiness but it's not so
much about the economics of happiness it
really is about understanding this
man-made artificial system absolutely
pumped up by fossil fuels those
high-rise buildings all the materials
that industrial food never really
impossible without fossil fuels and we
are now beginning to count the cost and
every level that man-made system it's
the economics of deep unhappiness and
deep ill health physically ill have
mounting day by day from diabetes to
heart disease to terrible also mental
illness anxiety depression suicide so
really what we're talking about is the
economics of unhappiness versus cultures
of happiness we're talking about moving
towards cultures of connection deep
interdependence and it might all sound a
bit exaggerated and and romantic but I
have to say that I see on a daily basis
evidence of how that coming home and
that reconnection really does make
people happier and healthier
that's where our work completely aligns
I mean the whole of regenerative
cultures and bringing culture to the
foreground again healing is and and
reconnecting with our ability as nature
to be
healing influence in the ecosystems we
inhabit undo this we've done for
centuries and that's really I see so
many people around the world waking up
to that message and and there's a real
like I like to call it the regeneration
rising like playing with the the
generation as generation that
regenerates and and it's it's a call
that people really are resonating with
there's a brilliant who just made a
documentary called 2040 that has the
subtitle join the regeneration and at
the conference in you do that so you
know they also put it all so again what
I said earlier you know so you create
that in the dominant narrative people
who are not in any way connected to this
movement they're being told the opposite
and they feel it they're saying this
human race is like a cancer I mean you
know we decide to extinguish ourselves
and the fact that we actually need
people on the land and I on this crowded
planet where so much damage has been
inflicted by the system we actually need
more people to care for every tree for
every earth one foot for that
regeneration and so once people connect
to that and not part of some kind of
productive meaningful activity and that
it is yeah and every level deeply joyful
and I'm so glad that you are a colleague
in this and thank you so much for you is
done you've been you've been such an
inspiration for so many years and and
also for me you you continue to be an
inspiration in the sense that you have
been so true to your message I like you
you just the world's catching up my mind
but you you have been doing this for
much longer than many and and and often
not with getting enough of the
recognition I still believe that there
wouldn't be in every Tesco in the
country of the UK there wouldn't be food
mileage stickers if you and Isaac hadn't
started conversations about the power of
local food and in distinguishing that
actually local can be even more
important than certified organic and
those kind of conversations I personally
believe that you've been very
influential in and taking that out to a
lot of people who now use that language
but have no idea that it came from
impulses organization saying thank you
so much because we haven't we also
haven't done very much to promote
ourselves it's been an absolute pleasure
and maybe the one final question would
be M despite everything would you say
you still hopeful for because the last
year has brought this particularly
around climate change a kind of strange
shift from arguing whether climate
change was as important as some people
or we all believe it is to suddenly
people saying well it's all too late and
doom and gloom and extinction and
collapse is near all that and where it
is positioning yourself in this dynamic
where we can embrace collapse of a
system that no longer serves but still
happy hopeful that that we can turn the
corner of becoming healers again and and
building a future for all of life and
for Humanity yes no I mean I definitely
feel there is hope I am as I say I'm
worried that this dominant system can
continue to escalate and create a lot of
damage so I see a certain sense of
urgency in getting the word out and
helping people make that transition into
being part of this new movement which
which I do see as a global movement in a
way even though it consists of a
multitude of different cultures and
people's so I think that it's wonderful
to know that what we can do right now
that will make our lives happier and
healthier is what we need to do for the
long-term and let's not dwell too much
in the distant future or even in
tomorrow because we've all well because
we've learned that
really living in the present and and
doing what we know is right is what we
what makes us happy and what will make
us below so once we learn those deeper
spiritual essence of being in the
present and doing what we know is right
we're on a part that you think is a
winner
however we look at it absolutely yeah
it's the the doing will change as we
change the being coming back into the
present that is the presence and
enacting from that joy of connecting
with people in place I come back to that
a lot that the pathway to make it
through the eye of the needle in the
face of adversity and the pathway to
building the resilience towards the
calamities that might still come is one
in the same pathway and in doing so we
can be healthier and happier and more
meaningful and that's really the message
we need to come back to so thank you so
much for this time I also just wanted to
ask you and add any more contact with
with Alan